Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Kathryn and today we're talking about a special kind of man.
我是Kathryn，今天我们聊一种特别的男人。
That's right.
没错。
Today we are, well, everyone starts living with your parents but as adults, some people
今天我们要讲的是，嗯，每个人一开始都和父母住，但成年后，有些人
still want to continue living with their parents.
仍然想继续和父母住在一起。
That's right.
没错。
So the topic of today's lesson is living with your parents when you're an adult.
所以今天课程的主题是成年后和父母同住。
Let's take a listen to the dialogue.
我们来听一下对话。
Why did your girlfriend break up with you?
你女朋友为什么和你分手？
I don't know.
我不知道。
She said she was tired of me not manning up and being more independent, which I think
她说她厌倦了我不像个男人、不够独立，我觉得
is all a bunch of crap.
这全是胡扯。
Well, you still live with your parents so she does have a point.
嗯，你还和父母住，所以她说的有道理。
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
A lot of people live with their parents, especially when rent is so expensive and the slump in
很多人和父母住，尤其是房租这么贵，经济又不景气的时候。
the economy.
Yeah, but you're almost 40.
是啊，但你都快40岁了。
Plus, you make good money so there's really no excuse.
而且你收入不错，所以真的没什么借口。
That's just simply because you're a mama's boy.
这纯粹是因为你是个妈宝男。
Whatever, dude.
随便你怎么说，哥们。
I have everything I need.
我需要的东西都有。
Why would I move out?
我为什么要搬出去？
Have a great roof over my head, my mom does my laundry and cooks for me.
头顶有好房子住，我妈给我洗衣服做饭。
What else could a guy ask for?
一个男人还能要求什么？
Let's agree to disagree.
我们求同存异吧。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now let's take a look at some language on Language Takeaway.
现在来看看“语言要点”中的一些语言点。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
The first verb we have here is to break up.
我们这里的第一个动词是“分手”。
So we heard the guy say, why did your girlfriend break up with you?
我们听到那个男人说：你女朋友为什么和你分手？
That's right.
没错。
So this is a phrasal verb and to break up in a relationship or in a romantic sense means
这是一个短语动词，在恋爱关系中，“分手”的意思是
to end a relationship.
结束一段关系。
So if you break up with your girlfriend, it means you end the relationship.
所以如果你和女朋友分手，意思就是你结束了这段关系。
That's right.
没错。
So you think about breaking something, it goes into pieces.
你可以想象“打破”某物，它碎成碎片。
Well, in a relationship, it means you both leave each other, you go your separate ways.
嗯，在关系中，它意味着你们彼此离开，各走各的路。
And so you can say, he broke up with me or we broke up.
所以你可以说：他和我分手了，或者我们分手了。
That's right.
没错。
And the reason his girlfriend broke up with him is because she said he was not independent.
他女朋友和他分手的原因是她觉得他不独立。
So she wanted him to be more independent.
所以她希望他更独立。
So independent means that you do things on your own.
所以“独立”意味着你自己做事。
When you're, you know, you do things alone.
当你，你知道，你独自做事。
You don't expect other people to help you.
你不指望别人帮你。
You don't depend on other people.
你不依赖别人。
Exactly.
完全正确。
So you can say, he's very independent.
所以你可以说：他非常独立。
He loves to travel alone.
他喜欢独自旅行。
Okay.
好的。
So it means that you don't really need other people's help, I guess, right?
所以它意味着你不太需要别人的帮助，我想，对吧？
Exactly.
完全正确。
Okay.
好的。
All right.
好了。
So he's not really very independent and well, his friend agrees.
所以他其实不太独立，嗯，他的朋友也同意。
He says, well, you know what?
他说：嗯，你知道吗？
I think she has a point.
我觉得她说的有道理。
To have a point means to say something that the other person agrees with.
“有道理”意思是说了一些对方同意的话。
Okay.
好的。
So you could say, he has a point.
所以你可以说：他说的有道理。
I agree with him.
我同意他。
That's a good argument.
这是个好论点。
Right.
对。
So if somebody says something and you agree with that, when you say, yeah, you have a
所以如果有人说了什么，你同意，当你说：是啊，你说的
point, it means you agree with the argument.
有道理，意思是你同意这个论点。
You agree with what that person says.
你同意那个人说的话。
All right.
好的。
And now lastly, because he lives with his parents, his friend is saying that he should
最后，因为他和父母住，他的朋友说他应该
move out.
搬出去。
You should move out.
你应该搬出去。
So here's another phrasal verb, to move out.
所以这里是另一个短语动词，“搬出去”。
This means that you leave the house and you find a new house.
这意味着你离开房子，找新房子。
So when you're with your parents, you want to move out.
所以当你和父母住时，你想搬出去。
That means you don't live with your parents anymore, but you find your own house.
这意味着你不再和父母住，而是找自己的房子。
That's right.
没错。
So, well, in general, when you find your own house, when you leave and your current place
所以，嗯，一般来说，当你找到自己的房子，离开你现在的
of living, that's moving out, right?
住处，那就是搬出去，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
So if I'm leaving the city, I move out of my house.
所以如果我要离开城市，我就搬出我的房子。
And then when I arrive in a new city, I move in to a new house.
然后当我到达新城市时，我就搬进新房子。
Oh, very good.
哦，很好。
So to move out and to move in, they go hand in hand.
所以搬出去和搬进来是相辅相成的。
All right.
好的。
So let's listen to the dialogue again and we'll be back with Fluency Builder.
那我们再听一遍对话，然后回来进行流利度训练。
Why did your girlfriend break up with you?
你女朋友为什么跟你分手？
I don't know.
我不知道。
She said she was tired of me not manning up and being more independent, which I think
她说她厌倦了我不够男子气概、不够独立，我觉得
is all a bunch of crap.
这全是胡扯。
Well, you still live with your parents, so she does have a point.
嗯，你还跟父母住在一起，所以她说的有道理。
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
A lot of people live with their parents, especially when rent is so expensive and the slump in
很多人跟父母住在一起，尤其是房租这么贵，经济又不景气的时候。
the economy.
经济不景气。
Yeah, but you're almost 40.
是啊，但你都快40岁了。
Plus, you make good money, so there's really no excuse.
而且你赚得不少，所以真的没什么借口。
It's just simply because you're a mama's boy.
纯粹是因为你是个妈宝男。
Whatever, dude.
随便你怎么说，哥们。
I have everything I need.
我需要的东西都有。
Why would I move out?
我为什么要搬出去？
I have a great roof over my head.
我有个好住处。
My mom does my laundry and cooks for me.
我妈帮我洗衣服、做饭。
What else could a guy ask for?
一个男人还能要求什么？
Let's agree to disagree.
我们各持己见吧。
All right.
好的。
So now four phrases for you on Fluency Builder.
现在流利度训练有四个短语。
Fluency Builder.
流利度训练。
So we've got a very interesting phrase here at the beginning of Fluency Builder today.
今天流利度训练开头有一个非常有趣的短语。
The phrase is manning up.
这个短语是“manning up”。
So the girlfriend was tired of the man not manning up.
所以女朋友厌倦了这个男人不够男子气概。
Right.
对。
So to man up.
所以“to man up”。
And what does that mean?
那是什么意思？
To man up to something?
对某事“man up”？
It means to be responsible or to be more mature or to be an adult about something.
意思是负责任、更成熟或像个成年人一样处理事情。
So maybe this guy, this man, he's kind of immature.
所以也许这个家伙，这个男人，有点不成熟。
He lives at home.
他住在家里。
He's not very responsible or independent.
他不太负责任或独立。
And his girlfriend wanted him to be more responsible, more independent.
他女朋友希望他更负责任、更独立。
So she wanted him to man up.
所以她希望他“man up”。
That's right.
没错。
So it usually means that you also should accept the consequences for your actions.
所以通常也意味着你应该为自己的行为承担后果。
Right.
对。
Exactly.
正是。
So you might push someone to man up, take responsibility for something and do it even
所以你可能催促某人“man up”，承担责任并去做某事，即使
though the consequences might not be fun or good.
后果可能不愉快或不好。
Now this remember is very, very much slang.
记住，这非常非常口语化。
So you don't say this in an essay or a paper.
所以不要在论文或文章里这么说。
This is what you say between friends.
这是朋友之间说的话。
Okay.
好的。
And another slang phrase here that we use to describe this man is a mama's boy.
还有一个口语短语用来描述这个男人，就是“mama's boy”。
He says, his friend says he's a mama's boy.
他说，他朋友说他是妈宝男。
Mama's boy.
妈宝男。
So mama is mother.
所以“mama”是妈妈。
Mama's boy means that he's very, very close with his mother.
“Mama's boy”意思是他跟妈妈非常非常亲近。
This is not a good thing to say.
这不是什么好话。
It's usually something that's a little bit critical.
通常有点批评意味。
Okay.
好的。
So say he's a mama's boy.
所以就说他是妈宝男。
Okay.
好的。
So his mother washes his clothes, she cooks his food, she does everything for him.
所以他妈妈给他洗衣服、做饭，什么都替他做。
Right.
对。
And he doesn't do anything for himself.
他自己什么都不做。
He's like a little baby.
他就像个小宝宝。
He's like a child and his mama, his mother does everything for him.
他像个孩子，他妈妈什么都替他做。
So it is a little bit like an insult, I guess.
所以这有点像侮辱，我想。
Yes.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
So it's not really a good thing to call someone a mama's boy unless in this situation, they're
所以叫别人妈宝男不是什么好事，除非在这种情况下，他们是
friends and his friend is saying, well, you know what?
朋友，他朋友在说，嗯，你知道吗？
It seems like you're a mama's boy.
看起来你是个妈宝男。
Exactly.
正是。
All right.
好的。
So our next phrase is when he was justifying and say, why would I move out?
下一个短语是他辩解时说，我为什么要搬出去？
Why would I leave my parents' house?
我为什么要离开父母家？
I have a great roof over my head.
我有个好住处。
So what does he mean by a great roof?
他说的“好屋顶”是什么意思？
Okay.
好的。
So the roof means the top of your house.
所以“roof”指的是房子的顶部。
You know, obviously our houses, they're not open.
你知道，显然我们的房子不是露天的。
They have a cover and that's called a roof.
它们有遮盖物，那叫屋顶。
But the phrase here, a roof over my head or a roof over one's head means a place to live.
但这里的短语“a roof over my head”或“a roof over one's head”意思是住的地方。
Okay.
好的。
A home.
一个家。
So if you say, I don't have a roof over my head, that means I don't have a home.
所以如果你说“我没有遮风挡雨的屋顶”，意思就是我没有家。
I don't have a house.
我没有房子。
Okay.
好的。
So he's saying that he has a great roof over his head.
所以他说他有一个很好的遮风挡雨的屋顶。
His mom does everything for him.
他妈妈为他做所有事情。
So he's like, why would I move out?
所以他就像在说，我为什么要搬出去？
And his friend ends the conversation by saying, you know what?
然后他的朋友结束对话时说，你知道吗？
Let's agree to disagree.
我们求同存异吧。
This is a really important phrase to learn, especially if you like to argue a lot.
这是一个非常重要的短语要学，特别是如果你喜欢争论的话。
In this case, one guy said, listen, living at home is good.
在这个例子中，一个人说，听着，住在家里挺好的。
It works for me.
对我来说很合适。
And the other said, no, it's not very responsible.
另一个人说，不，这样不太负责任。
I agree with your girlfriend.
我同意你女朋友的看法。
And at the end, they still believe what they thought originally.
最后，他们仍然坚持自己最初的想法。
So they agree to disagree.
所以他们同意求同存异。
That means they're not going to argue anymore, but they're not going to change their minds.
这意味着他们不会再争论了，但也不会改变自己的想法。
Right.
对。
So I respect your opinion and you respect my opinion and the conversation is over.
所以我尊重你的意见，你尊重我的意见，对话就结束了。
So Marco, chocolate ice cream is clearly the best ice cream.
所以马可，巧克力冰淇淋显然是最好的冰淇淋。
Vanilla ice cream is the best.
香草冰淇淋才是最好的。
Yeah, no, I think chocolate has more flavor.
嗯，不，我觉得巧克力味道更浓。
No, vanilla is tastier.
不，香草更好吃。
Okay, let's agree to disagree.
好吧，我们求同存异吧。
I still think chocolate is the best.
我还是觉得巧克力是最好的。
Marco still thinks vanilla is the best, but we're not going to argue anymore.
马可还是觉得香草是最好的，但我们不会再争论了。
Okay, great.
好的，很好。
So let's listen to our dialogue one last time.
那我们最后再听一遍对话吧。
Why did your girlfriend break up with you?
你女朋友为什么和你分手？
I don't know.
我不知道。
She said she was tired of me not manning up and being more independent, which I think
她说她厌倦了我不像个男人、不够独立，我觉得
is all a bunch of crap.
这全是胡扯。
Well, you still live with your parents, so she does have a point.
嗯，你还和父母住在一起，所以她说的有道理。
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
A lot of people live with their parents, especially when rent is so expensive and the slump in
很多人和父母住在一起，尤其是房租这么贵、经济
the economy.
不景气的时候。
Yeah, but you're almost 40.
是啊，但你都快40岁了。
Plus, you make good money, so there's really no excuse.
而且你收入不错，所以真的没什么借口。
It's just simply because you're a mama's boy.
这纯粹是因为你是个妈宝男。
Whatever, dude.
随便你怎么说，哥们。
I have everything I need.
我什么都不缺。
Why would I move out?
我为什么要搬出去？
Have a great roof over my head.
我有个很好的遮风挡雨的屋顶。
My mom does my laundry and cooks for me.
我妈妈帮我洗衣服、做饭。
What else could a guy ask for?
一个男人还能要求什么？
Let's agree to disagree.
我们求同存异吧。
All right, so talking about a mama's boy living at home.
好了，所以我们在讨论一个住在家里妈宝男。
Now, as he mentioned, in the United States, kids usually leave home when they're 18 or
就像他提到的，在美国，孩子们通常在18或
19 when they go to college, right?
19岁上大学时离开家，对吧？
But in other places, like in Latin America or even, for example, in many parts of Europe,
但在其他地方，比如拉丁美洲，甚至欧洲很多地方，
people will live at home until they're 24 or 26 because it is expensive to live by yourself.
人们会一直住在家里直到24或26岁，因为独自生活很贵。
It is, and so in a lot of these countries, you hear people maybe joking about the men
确实如此，所以在很多这些国家，你可能会听到人们开玩笑说
being mama's boys.
男人是妈宝男。
Like Italy, for example, this is often something that people like to joke about.
比如意大利，这是人们喜欢开玩笑的话题。
Obviously, it's not true in most cases, but it is true that a lot of people live with
显然，大多数情况下这不是真的，但确实很多人
their families until later because, like you say, it's expensive or maybe in their culture,
和家里人住到很晚，因为像你说的，生活成本高，或者在他们文化中，
in their tradition, you don't leave your home until you get married.
传统上，你直到结婚才离开家。
Right, because it could be also for religious reasons.
对，也可能是因为宗教原因。
Exactly, and so I think it differs from culture to culture, but this idea of a mama's boy
没错，所以我认为这因文化而异，但妈宝男这个概念
is very, very much a part of American culture.
在美国文化中非常非常普遍。
We often talk about this.
我们经常谈论这个。
We often joke about it, and sometimes you say, oh, you're such a mama's boy because
我们经常拿它开玩笑，有时你会说，哦，你真是个妈宝男，因为
my brother sometimes, he calls my mom a lot.
我哥哥有时候经常给我妈打电话。
I say, oh, you're such a mama's boy, always calling mom.
我就说，哦，你真是个妈宝男，总是给妈妈打电话。
Now, obviously, this works for guys, but what about girls?
现在，这显然适用于男人，那女人呢？
Would you say like daddy's girl?
你会说“爸爸的乖女儿”吗？
Yeah, a little bit.
嗯，有点。
It's usually girls who get everything they want from their dads.
通常是指那些从爸爸那里得到一切想要的女孩。
Like, daddy, I want a new car.
比如，爸爸，我想要辆新车。
Daddy, I want new clothes.
爸爸，我想要新衣服。
Yeah, so daddy's girl is someone who is very close with their dad and maybe is able
是的，所以“爸爸的乖女儿”是指和爸爸关系非常亲密，可能能
to have him give her lots of stuff that she wants.
让他给她很多她想要的东西的人。
So we don't really hear like daddy's boy or mama's girl very often, right?
所以我们很少听到“爸爸的乖儿子”或“妈妈的乖女儿”，对吧？
No, it's the opposite.
不，是相反的。
It's always the opposite.
总是相反的。
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
是的，是的，没错。
Well, it's a very interesting topic, and I'm sure many of you in your different cultures
嗯，这是个很有趣的话题，我相信你们很多人在不同的文化中
may also continue living with your parents, or maybe it's not common, or maybe even after
可能也会继续和父母住在一起，或者可能不常见，或者甚至在
marriage in many parts of Asia, people get married and live at home with their in-laws.
亚洲很多地方，人们结婚后会和公婆住在一起。
That's right, so we're very curious to hear about your experience in your country.
没错，所以我们非常好奇想听听你在自己国家的经历。
If you have such a thing as a mama's boy or a daddy's girl, let us know.
如果你们那里也有“妈宝男”或“爸宝女”这种说法，请告诉我们。
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站是 EnglishPod.com。
All right, we'll see you guys there.
好了，我们到时候在那儿见。
Bye.
再见。